there are three main aspects that create
a profitable Trader number one is their
ability to handle their emotions
otherwise known as trading psychology
number two is their ability to handle
risk otherwise known as risk management
and number three last but certainly not
least is their ability to create a
strategy that fits their trading style
but most importantly creates a
money-making Edge over the market
mastering all three of these nearly
guarantees that you will be a profitable
Trader but missing even one of them can
nearly guarantee the opposite so in
today's video I'll be teaching you my
exact process of building profitable
trading strategies all the way from
concept to creation of the strategy to
testing and even optimizing that trading
strategy and by the time you come away
from this video you will have the
capability to create your own profitable
trading strategy yourself so if you're
someone interested in creating your own
strategy or even optimizing a strategy
you've learned from someone else this
video is for you go ahead and click that
like button for me go ah aead And
subscribe if you are new and I'll see
you right after the intro and
[Music]
disclaimer yes I noticed that in that
intro my necklace was sitting on my
shirt like this and it bothered me too
so she's getting tucked for the rest of
the video but let's go ahead and get
started with the video so the first step
of creating a trading strategy is to
understand the concept of the trading
strategy you're going to create and
there are two maor major Concepts that
90% of trading strategies fall into
these two concepts are very simple the
first one is a trend continuation
concept this is exactly what it sounds
like it's any strategy that attempts to
follow the trend that would be things
like a pullback strategy where you try
to capture the bottom of a pullback it
would be things like a breakout strategy
where you're still trying to capture the
continuation of that Trend that's
concept number one concept number two is
the counter Trend and or reversal
concept this is exactly what it sounds
like this is when you're looking for a
market that's trending in a certain
direction like this uptrend and then
loses momentum and with this concept
you're trying to capture the top of this
move in order to sell in anticipation
for the trend to completely reverse now
the reason the first step in creating a
trading strategy is to understand the
concept you're going to create this
strategy around is because once we
understand the concept of the trading
strategy we can create logical rules
around that concept that can give us a
profitable trading strategy for example
if you just say I'm a trend continuation
Trader chances are you're not going to
be profitable but if you create a set of
logical rules that give you an edge over
the market based around Trend
continuation trading then you're one
step closer to having a profitable
trading strategy and becoming a
profitable Trader utilizing Trend
continuation so the first step to
creating a trading strategy is to pick
the concept that you want to trade based
on whether that be train continu ation
or counter Trend the second step is to
build the strategy using logical rules
that align with whatever concept you
chose and that can create an edge over
the market so this is the framework I
use when building any profitable trading
strategy it is called
C this stands for conditions entry
stoploss and Target now in terms of
conditions conditions are just
everything you need to see before you
place an entry some examples of this
would be things like Trend things like
structure support and resistance supply
and demand order blocks things like
indicators specific indicators going
oversold or overball or having
Divergence or having some type of
crossover conditions could be chart
patterns like double tops or bottoms
like a flag pattern like a head and
shoulders pattern and another condition
could be price like an even handled
number now these are just the top
conditions that I personally use when
building strategies there's obviously
unlimited conditions that you could
utilize when creating a strategy but
these are the examples of the ones I use
the most next up is entries after all of
your conditions are met why are you
going to press the button this is
something a lot of Traders have a
problem with and because of that they're
inconsistent in their trading you need
an exact reason that you press the buy
button or press the sell button so what
is that reason for me the top ones that
I use are Candlestick patterns such as
engulfing Hammer shooting star candles
breakouts like flag patterns are just
breakouts of a resistance or support
level chart patterns like double tops
and double bottoms and I rarely use this
but I have specific strategies where I
utilize the RSI coming out of oversold
and once that happens that may be my
entry so that's just to give you some
examples of the things I use just like
conditions there are unlimited entries
that you can try when creating a
strategy next is our stoploss stop-loss
is very self-explanatory where am I
going to get out if I'm wrong about a
specific trade and finally our Target
where am I getting out if I'm right
these two are super important you never
want to get into a trade without an idea
of where you're getting out if you're
wrong because unlike popular belief that
thinks professional trading means that
you somehow have like a crystal ball and
you can tell the future of the market
that's not true professional Traders
even when you become a professional and
a profitable Trader you will have losses
and your ability to handle those losses
is extremely important one of the best
ways to ensure that you don't lose more
than you're willing to on a specific
trade is to set a stop loss where you
know you're wrong and you want to get
out of the trade and having an idea of
where you're going to get out if you're
right is really important as well so now
we've covered the top two trading
strategy Concepts as well as the
framework to building any profitable
trading strategy let's move on now to
building a profitable day trading
strategy so first off the concept of the
strategy you're about to learn is Trend
continuation so we're looking to follow
the trend with this strategy we're also
going to be utilizing two different time
frames with this strategy the four 4our
chart and the 15minute chart we're going
to utilize the 4-Hour chart to find our
Trend and the 15-minute chart to find
some accurate entries now let me zoom
out and I'm going to give you a big
picture idea of what we're trying to
accomplish with this strategy then I'll
explain to you all the tools you're
going to need in order to execute this
trading strategy so first off if we take
a look at the chart you can see that we
have the 4-Hour chart here and the
15-minute chart here well the 4H hour
chart what we're going to pay attention
to is this pullback right here and
remember the 4H hour chart is where
we're identifying Trend but on the
15minute chart this pullback because the
15-minute chart is made up of a lot of
candles where the 4H hour chart isn't
going to be made up of as many candles
the 15-minute chart is going to look
more like the start of a downtrend so I
want to explain this so you understand
that we're looking for Trend on the 4
Hour and we do not care what the
15-minute looks like because during a
pullback on the 4 Hour the 15-minute
chart is going to be looking like a Down
Trend throughout that pullback so what
we're going to be doing is utilizing the
trend again on the 4-Hour chart to give
us the bias of the direction we want to
trade then we're going to be waiting for
this pullback to start once that
pullback starts we're going to be
dropping down to the 15-minute time
frame and we're actually going to be
utilizing the RSI indicator we're going
to be waiting for oversold and then
waiting for Divergence along with an
entry reason which I'll be explaining in
just a second but after we get that RSI
Divergence and an entry reason that is a
great reason Reon to assume that this 4H
hour pullback might be over we can get a
really nice entry cuz we're on the
15-minute chart with a small stop loss
and hopefully ride the continuation of
this trend for some massive profits
first things first let's go ahead and
plot all the tools we need onto the
chart we're going to need the 50 EMA to
help us identify the trend on the 4H
hour chart we're going to need the RSI
indicator to help us identify oversold
and overbought and also Divergence and
we're need the ATR indicator to help
with stoploss placement so I'm going to
go ahead and put all those on the screen
with we're on a blank chart right now
I'm just going to type in EMA slap that
on the chart the
RSI and finally the ATR indicator I'm
going to move the ATR to the top that's
just where I like to have it and now
we'll change the settings of these
indicators appropriately for the EMA we
go to inputs we want this to be a 50
period exponential moving average and
for the RSI indicator I actually want
this to be a length of 10 I want it to
move a little faster for this strategy I
also get rid of the RSI based ma because
I don't use that but once you do that
you are all set now I'm going to be
teaching you the full detailed rules for
this trading strategy so let's Dive
Right In we're going to do this in the
framework that you learned earlier
conditions entries stops and targets the
C framework so obviously we're going to
be starting with conditions so for the
conditions of this strategy the first
thing we want to do is look at the 4our
chart we want to make sure the 4our
chart is trading above the 50 period
exponential moving average we just
plotted on the chart that is very
self-explanatory obviously we want to
see price above that moving average once
we see that we want to start to see a
pullback when we start to see a pullback
we're going to drop down to the 15minute
Chart I'll do that now on the 15minute
chart we want to see that the RSI goes
oversold on the RSI indicator oversold
means under 30 which is this little
green line you can see down here on my
chart as you can see RSI is in fact
under 30 right now so with that being
the case we have condition one met
because on the 4our chart we're trading
above the 50 EMA and we have condition
two met because the RSI is oversold what
do you think we're looking for next that
would obviously be condition number
three which is the RSI creates
Divergence to give you a little lesson
on Divergence it is extremely simple if
price is making lower lows while the
indicator creates a higher low like this
higher low lower low that is called
Divergence so if price is making lower
lows and the indicator is diverging from
that by making higher lows we call that
Divergence we're on the RSI indicator so
obviously we're going to be utilizing
RSI Divergence and that's our last
condition for this strategy so let's
push the market forward a bit and after
zooming in a bit to make this really
easy for you to see as you can see we
have price creating a low then a low or
low and if we look down here on the RSI
indicator we have a low on the RSI
followed by what followed by by a higher
low so does that meet the criteria for
bullish RSI Divergence the answer is yes
so that's our third condition we want to
see price making a lower low while the
RSI indicator makes a higher low in
other words RSI Divergence and obviously
this is for a bullish entry I didn't
mention that at the beginning but again
should be self-explanatory so after
conditions what's next well in
CST next after conditions would be the
entry reason the entry reason in this
case very simple a bullish engulfing
candle after all of our conditions are
met so after all of our conditions are
met the entry is going to be a candle
that completely engulfs the previous
candle or in other words a green candle
with a larger body than the previous red
candle body that is what's called an
engulfing candle now important note
about this engulfing candle it either
needs to be the swing low or directly
follow the swing low that was created
with this Divergence I'll say that one
more time the engulf candle either needs
to be the swing low or needs to come
directly after the swing low that
created the Divergence what I mean by
that is a situation like this would not
classify as a valid entry utilizing the
engulfing candle that I'm talking about
and the reason is here does this
engulfing candle because we obviously
have an engulfing candle but is it the
swing low or does it directly follow the
swing low of this low the answer is no
this is the swing swing low of this low
this candle comes afterwards but is not
the swing low and it's not directly
following it so that's a really
important part of this entry as well and
I also have a second entry that I'm
going to share with you if you stay
until the end and if I have time I'm
trying to make this video as short as
possible although it's really difficult
to explain how to build a full trading
strategy in a small amount of time so a
quick recap before we go over stops and
targets for our conditions we want to
see price trading above the 50 EMA on
the 4H hour chart we then want to see a
pullback start at that point dropping
down to the 15minute looking at the RSI
to see that it goes oversold then
looking for RSI Divergence after that
our actual entry reason the reason I'm
going to be pressing the buy button on a
bullish trade is going to be based on a
bullish engulfing candle at that point I
pressed the buy button now let's move on
to stops and targets for this strategy
so for the stop loss on this strategy
we're going to take the value of the ATR
indicator at the time of the entry
candle and we're going to multiply that
by two that sounds complicated it's not
at all the average true range is what we
plotted on the chart earlier I put it on
top of my screen if you look right here
you can see this number we discount the
last number so this would be four Pips
which means that the value of the ATR
indicator when this candle was printed
was four Pips for my stop loss I'm just
taking that multiplying it by two and
that's my stop loss so in this case 4 *
2 obviously eight Pips is going to be my
stop loss I'll grab a position tool
entry would be right in there stop loss
would be eight Pips which puts the stop
loss right here and for a Target on
these examples I'm just going to do a
1.4 to1 reward to risk ratio feel free
to test for whatever targets you would
like to suggestion I would test for
targets back up at the highs that were
created before the pullback on the 4H
hour chart that's one of my favorite
ways to take targets but for today's
example we're going to utilize fixed
targets at a 1.4 to1 reward to risk
ratio so one more time for our stop loss
we're taking a look at the value of this
ATR indicator which we can see right up
here in the top left and we're just
multiplying that by two from our entry
point that is going to be our stop loss
so eight Pips from the actual entry and
now we have this entire trade set up and
ready to go let's click play and see
what happens to the
market as you can see price quickly
pushed up high enough to hit those
targets so that is a complete example of
a bullish version of this trading
strategy I hope you guys have enjoyed
the training so far if you have you
would very likely enjoy being a part of
the TTC Forex University in the
University we have a full training
course that goes all the way from the
complete basics of Forex to extremely
Advanced strategies that I trade in the
markets every single day on top of that
I also send out two to five email alerts
of Trades I'm actually taking based on
the strategies students are learning
inside of the University and on top of
that it's a mentorship program meaning
that any questions you have you can
actually ask and it'll be me personally
answering any of the questions you have
about the training or about trading in
general so if that sounds at all
interesting to you go ahead and click
the top Link in the description or go to
www.th trading channel.com to get all
the details about the TTC Forex
University if you're not interested in
that no big deal at all let's move on
now and take a look at a bearish example
of this trading strategy same exact
rules here they are just flipped upside
down so on our 4our chart instead of
making sure price is above the 50 EMA
here on a bearish version of this
trading strategy we're making sure price
is trading below the 50 EMA which is our
blue line here after we make sure price
is in fact trading below the 50 EMA we
then want to drop down to a 15-minute
chart once we start to see this pullback
so let's go down to a 15-minute chart
now here on the 15minute chart what do
we want to see we want to see the RSI
indicator go OB or over balt here is the
RSI indicator going over balt on this
swing High the next thing we want to see
is bearish Divergence which means that
we have a higher high in price like this
and the RSI creates a lower high like
this that's what we're looking for next
we're looking for that RSI Divergence
let's go ahead and see what happens if
we push price forward there we have a
higher high and after one red candle is
when we can classify this as Divergence
so at this this point we have a high
followed by a higher high on price and a
red candle which tells us that we do in
fact have RSI Divergence bearish RSI
Divergence what's next well now all of
our conditions are met the next thing
we're going to look for is our entry
which in this case is a bearish
engulfing candle it is the opposite of a
bullish engulfing candle meaning in this
case we're looking for a red candle that
completely engulfs the body of the
previous green candle do we get that
right here yes we do so with that being
the case we can actually go ahead and
set up this trade I'll put a short
position tool on the chart do you
remember what our stop loss was it was
two times the value of the ATR indicator
right now the ATR is seven so with that
being the case we would have a 14 pip
stop loss on this trade and with today's
Targets on these examples being a 1.4
to1 reward to risk ratio this would be
that entire trade setup let's now click
play and see what happened as you can
see directly after entering this trade
did in fact push down far enough to hit
targets before we move on to the next
lesson I want to make this very clear
these were just examples of winning
trades this strategy also has losses
just like any other strategy trading in
general is not about knowing exactly
what the Market's going to do next it's
about having an edge it's about
mathematics if you have a strategy that
wins over 50% of the time and you have a
reward to risk ratio that averages over
a 1:1 then you are going to be
profitable in the the long run that's
just how the math adds up so keep in
mind that this strategy obviously has
wins but obviously it has losses as well
congratulations we have now built an
entire rules-based trading strategy
together but that's not the end of the
work we have to do you see a strategy
it's like an idea or a theory and just
like any other idea or Theory it needs
to be tested and validated to prove that
it works or is likely to work in the
future future whenever you're done
creating the strategy you need to look
at it like you're a mad scientist and
you're just going to experiment until
you find out what works all this
experimentation is called back testing
this is the process of taking the exact
rules we have created for this strategy
and going through the past 100 instances
that those rules occurred that this
strategy happened on a specific currency
pair and documenting those results
documenting things like the date and
time documenting things like whether or
not the trade won or lost your reward to
risk ratio documenting all the
information you want in order to
validate that the idea you had or that
the trading strategy you've created is
in fact likely to be profitable in the
future so simply put back testing is
just taking whatever strategy you've
created and testing it through historic
data in order to ensure that it's
something profitable to trade with and
so now let's go over some key points of
back testing first off what are you
going to need in order to back test a
trading strategy where you're going to
need some type of spreadsheet to record
this data in so for me I like to use
this one that I created it has columns
for everything that I want to record in
my back test and along with that it does
some pretty cool automatic calculations
to show me what the predicted outcome of
this trading strategy may be so if you
don't have one of these you will need a
spreadsheet of some kind to keep up with
this information now if you want to get
this one for absolutely free we actually
give it away with our free beginner
course so if you go sign up for our
Absol absolutely free beginner course we
send this to you through email so that
you have it throughout your process of
learning how to trade in that beginner
course so if you want this one for
absolutely free then you can go to the
link in the description that's labeled
free beginner course and we'll send it
directly to your inbox so let's do one
trade together just to ensure that you
have a handle on this this was the
bearish example of our strategy as you
can see down here we have our bearish
Divergence on the RSI we have a higher
high here and we have our red engulfing
candle covered in this green line so if
I was actually back testing this I would
wait for this to occur I would put a
position tool on the chart I would set
my stops and targets accordingly then I
would see how the trade played out if
the trade played out as a win this is
exactly what I would do I would come
over here to my spreadsheet I would put
in the pair which is the dollar
Canada the time of this trade which is
10:15 the date of this trade which is
311 my stop- loss on this trade which
was 14 Pips and my target which was 20
Pips and then I would move on to the
next trade I would literally do this 100
times for the last 100 trades that
happened with this exact strategy I
would record that data and that's the
process of back testing that's what
proves to you that you're going to be
trading something in live markets that
is a profitable strategy and has a very
high likelihood of making money in the
future now outside of a spreadsheet I
get a lot of questions about how to back
test something that is a multiple time
frame strategy it's actually really easy
on trading view there's a little button
I'll try to zoom in or point it out
right up here the square that you can
see that I just put a circle around
which just seems weird this square if
you click it you can go and actually get
this little double setup and if you
click one of them and leave it on the 15
and then click another one you can put
the other one on a 4our chart and with
this being the case I now have the
visuals of a 4our chart down here and a
15minute chart up here now something
else that's really helpful is to go to
these settings down here and you want to
go ahead and click Crosshair for sure
you want to make sure you can see the
Crosshair on both of the charts and
that's what these settings are it's
sinking the layout so this is a dual
chart layout and you want to sync it up
you want to sync it up with the time the
Crosshair you do not want to sync the
time interval because we are doing
separate time intervals so that would
make no sense cuz we're doing a 15 and a
4 hour so you don't want that synced and
that's essentially it and the beauty of
this is it makes testing strategies with
multiple time frames very easy the
bottom right now is my 4our chart on the
4our chart what am I trying to do I'm
trying to make sure that price is below
the 50 EMA so at this point I can see
that price is still below the 50 EMA and
I can also look up here on my top chart
which is my 15 minute chart and on this
chart I can see that I have RSI going
over Bal
Divergence with a higher high on price
lower high on RSI and an entry and I can
also see that that entry was a winner so
using this multiple chart layout is how
I back test strategies that utilize
multiple time frame I feel like that may
have been confusing just because you
could barely see my crosshairs on the
screen so I made them a lot darker now
you can see my Crosshair on the bottom
chart and on the top chart since I can
see it on the bottom chart I can tell
when price is above the 50 EMA like
right now and when price is below it
like way back here so with this being
the case I really just have to pay
attention to the top chart for possible
trades and keep an eye out down the
bottom chart for a possible change in
the trend based on the 50 EMA to give
you an example of that I'm looking on
the 15minute up here I can tell on the 4
Hour chart that I am obviously above the
50 EMA throughout this entire section
here I'm still above the 50 EMA I can
tell that again by looking at the bottom
chart on the 4H hour chart and here we
have that RSI Divergence we have a trade
right here the reason is we have RSI
Divergence from the previous low to the
new higher low and we have a lower low
in price all this followed by this
engulfing candle so this is the way I
would go about physically back testing
the strategy is by utilizing the Dual
chart setup I showed you how to do just
a second ago and if it helps I would
make my crosshairs really dark like I
have them here now with that said that
is back testing in a nutshell but I'm
actually going to go ahead and show you
the results I got give you an idea of
what that actually looks like here you
can see a lot of red and green vertical
lines on my chart I'm actually just
going to pick one of these to get this
less confusing as you can see all of
these lines are those trades all these
lines are the back test I personally
just did from the very beginning of 2024
to today's date I normally utilize these
green and red vertical lines and the
reason is because it shows me the date
and time which just makes it that much
easier whenever I'm plugging these
numbers into a spreadsheet so I would
suggest using vertical lines like this
in your own testing but throughout 2024
this strategy has performed very well
here on the dollar Canada giving 22 wins
18 losses which is a 55% win rate with a
1.4 to1 Target this test was done
utilizing the exact same rules you have
learned throughout this video just
wanted to give you an idea of what that
looks like on a chart and if you end up
going out and testing the strategy
comment your results below to let other
Traders know what they can expect once
they start their back testing Journey
utilizing this strategy now moving on to
the final part of creating your very
first trading strategy from scratch the
final part is the optimization process
now this process can be as easy or as
difficult as you want it to be
personally I do kind of a minimal
optimization process I only optimize for
three different things once I back test
a trading strategy I normally back test
it on all the currency pairs you can see
on the right side of my screen all the
way down here to the New Zealand dollar
from there up to the euro dollar these
are the currency pairs that I normally
test with any strategy that I create and
the first step in my optimization
process is to pick the best performing
currency pairs now with this I pick the
top three to six performing currency
pairs with that specific strategy and
those are the currency pairs that I
trade with that strategy because they
have historically shown to be the best
performing pairs so those are the ones I
want in my Arsenal for my trading
strategy and in my Arsenal for my full
trading plan that's the first step of
optimization that I do the second step
of optimization is to find the best
Target for the highest Roi or win rate
depending on what you're going for if
you want a high win rate strategy you
may have to sacrifice some of your Roi
which is return on investment your
overall what you gain is what that is so
if you want a higher win rate you may
have to sacrifice that because you're
going have to go with a lower reward to
risk ratio on your trades to get a
higher win rate but I tend to to go for
the best targets for the best Roi in my
own optimization process this is
something you can do while back testing
as well optimizing and back testing kind
of go hand inand but I wanted to make
sure that this list was as organized and
as comprehensible as possible next up
after optimizing for the best targets
you obviously have to optimize for the
times that you can trade so you're going
to look through your back tested data
and make sure all the winning trades
didn't happen at a time where you could
not be around your computer when you're
taking your kids to school when you're
asleep you want to make sure that you
are still profitable even when you're
limited to only the time where you can
be behind your computer actually trading
so this is my optimization process yours
can be wildly different you can make
this as complicated and complex as you
would like to I just keep mine very
simple by optimizing for these three
things if you enjoyed today's video and
you're looking for a little extra help
in your trading then chances are you
would benefit from becoming a student in
the TTC Forex University our mentorship
program we have some space available in
that and again it comes with a full
course going from the complete basics of
Forex all the way to Advanced strategies
and everything in between it also comes
with two to five of my on trades that
I'm taking each week getting sent
directly to your email inbox and it is a
mentorship program meaning that I'll be
there to help guide you through your
process of becoming a profitable Trader
so if that's something you're interested
in go ahead and click that top Link in
the description or go to www.th trading
channel.com if that's not something
you're interested in no big deal at all
just be sure you're subscribed here be
sure to like the video if you made it
all the way to the end comment and say
that you made it to the end and I'll try
to like every comment that says that
it's Friday so I hope you have a great
weekend I hope you trade green next week
and I'll talk to you in the next video
see you soon